[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is Majjhima Nikaya 108, called Gopaka Moggallāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's when Venerable Ananda was living in the squirrel sanctuary, not long after the Blessed One had attained final nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Brahmin continues to ask,
[SPEAKER_00]: Master Nanda, Master Gautama was living at Vesali, in the hall of the peak roof in the great wood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, I went there and approached the Master, and in many ways, he gave a talk about meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Master Gautama was a meditator, cultivated meditation, and he praised every type of meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every type of meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: He did.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Blessed One did not praise every type of meditation, nor did he condemn every type of meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the only meditation you praised was a meditation of jhānas, or being able to be quite secluded from sensual pleasures, one then meditates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Meditation is about secluding yourself from sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, understanding the extent of the sensual domain, the depth of sense desire, and surmounting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And not just in the sense of, oh, I don't have any desire right now, so I'm ready to meditate.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, in other sutras, the Buddha would say, a monk would review his mind, like, is there a central desire in me now?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Next question then is, well, are there things in me now, on account of which a future central desire can manifest?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't just stop by, okay, I don't have any desire, so I'm fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I don't have any particular desire, but am I still liable to desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: If things change, if something comes along within my senses, could I not have sense... would I guarantee that I will not have sensual desire arising in me, because I abandon everything that's a necessary basis for that sensuality?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, there you go, that's your work.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, understanding the extent of your sensual desire, and understanding things on account of which sensual desire arises,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, things that you carry here and now, not like when, oh, in the future, when sensual desire arises, deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha would say, before it's manifested, you want to discern things in your mind, that are there, on account of which future sensual desire will be manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: That main... Well, the main reason for that is the lack of context, lack of the perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, as the Buddha said, improper ayoniso, manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is not a single thing that would bring un-arisen sensual desire to arise and the arisen one to increase as improper or that ayoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, loss of perspective on account of your own existence, situation, that's the sole reason why sensuality would increase or arise again.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what would be the main loss of perspective?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, paying attention to the sign of the beautifulism.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, see, that's already... paying that type of attention, it's already the result of you losing the perspective on a more fundamental level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, yoniso manasikāra is not like proper attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, oh, you're attending to this, you focus on certain things, and then everything else gets excluded.
[SPEAKER_01]: As we discussed before, yoniso manasikāra is basically the root, the origin of whatever you're attending.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I'm attending beautiful objects in the world, or if I'm attending ugly objects in the world, yoniso, aspect of that manasikāra, of that attention, is my perspective on the whole situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's where my attention is rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, you would be attending to the beautiful signs, for example, because your perspective sends you that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your perspective forgets the danger of attending to beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: It forgets the peril of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, next thing you know, you're attending to beautiful signs, because you forgot, you lost the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what yoniso manasikāra is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that fundamental perspective that then directs your attention this way or that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why there isn't such a single thing that could bring sensuality to increase and non-arisen one to arise, as loss of that perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: On that fundamental level.
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, if you never completely lose perspective on the fact that sensuality is dangerous, no word engaging in, pleasure of enunciation is much greater if you develop it, even... doesn't matter how many sensual objects might come your way, that perspective will keep your attention in check, so you will not attending... you will not be attending carelessly to these aspects that would then take you into sensual desire and sensual acts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that in itself is already meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when one wants to meditate, that's... that's what meditation is, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Developing the strength of your mind, that will take you away from sensuality, not maintain you within it, and then make it grow further.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same, we discussed that in a number of talks.
[SPEAKER_01]: People can find them in that jhāna playlist.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the first jhāna, the way it's described, says, withdrawn from sensuality, from unwholesome states, you experience joy and pleasure on account of withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, your mind is established in the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But somehow, that got perverted in a course of time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, people think is, okay, I'll just say no temporarily to my desires, do a meditation technique, get this special, super refined, pleasurable experience, and that's my jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: As if, like, chasing the pleasure of your focusing is the jhāna practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, the Buddha said that pleasure that people chase on account of jhāna, it's actually pleasure of renouncing the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, jhāna is the result of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, jhāna follows only later, once you have been withdrawn from centrality, through and through, as it says in that sutta, knowing the gratification, the escape from it, your liability, you abandon the basis that makes you liable to centrality, through understanding, through discernment, through not losing the context, because you become more and more familiar with that right perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you will experience joy on account of being withdrawn, fundamentally,
[SPEAKER_01]: From that sensual... from sensual domain in general.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not this particular sense desire or that.
[SPEAKER_01]: In general, sense desire as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's extremely pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that pleasure is something that your craving cannot take up, because you haven't done it through your action.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the result of you withdrawing from from all the pleasures you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasures of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by being withdrawn from pleasure of sensuality,
[SPEAKER_01]: The side effect of that is pleasure of renunciation, which is why the Buddha said you don't have to fear that pleasure of renunciation, because it's not underlined by craving, cannot be underlined by craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the same said for the jhāna then.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that pleasure of renunciation, if you cultivate, your mind then gets established in the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So first is renunciation, understanding sensual domain, pleasure on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That might take, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, jhāna is even a further symptom.
[SPEAKER_01]: A subsequent symptom that comes on account of you being withdrawn from sensuality and dwelling, as the Buddha would say, in that state.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you go to the toilet, extend your arm, eat, stand, lay down, walk,
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be abiding in that divine state.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I think I can meditate before that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be meditating within the sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what it would have meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would be meditating with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not incidental.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in that sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: In another sutta that uses the same description of meditating with sensuality, but then it also gives the similes of how would you meditate with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And each and every simile, basically, what it has in common is a focusing practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like praying upon a sort of... whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: A cat prays upon a mouse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, what are you... you're trying to get something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's the point, that's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you are not withdrawn from sensual domain, on account of which you then experience the pleasure and then jhāna develops, you... whatever effort you make will be rooted in the sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: In trying to get pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't necessarily think about pleasure, in thinking that you can perform things towards the right meditation, as opposed to understand things that will make you withdrawn from them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the whole point of samādhi is viveka from unwholesome, literally, seclusion from unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't do that on account of your unwholesome state.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only withdraw yourself by undoing, basically, your lack of perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are within unwholesome because you don't have perspective on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start developing perspective through contemplating unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: The gratification, the danger, the escape in regard to desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, oh, by focusing on this, and after three seconds I do this, and then I move that, and then I watch this step, and then the fourth step, and then I look at this moment, and then that moment, and then the next moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's you laying out what you're gonna do fully within on account of your sensual desires already.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even the hope of practicing the dhamma is rooted in sensuality for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're going that way of sensual development.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the Buddha did not go into specifics of, like, what you would be doing on account of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: He just said, unless you abandon the sensual domain, you will be meditating with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: How?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he said, like a cat waiting for a mouse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a bird waiting for a fish.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm focusing, concentrating on one point, where the mouse will show itself, and then I'll pounce.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, I will get it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, I will grab that jhāna, and I will have that supreme pleasure of jhāna, and I'll be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, on account of that, you're not... you're even further away from jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're chasing it as pleasure, failing to see the pleasure is secondary product of your withdrawal from sensuality, and then the jhāna is tertiary product of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having abandoned sensuality, he experienced joy on account of that withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, in that state of joyous contentment of renunciation, his mind enters and dwells, abides, in that state of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: After.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're saying about... you have to understand what sensuality is, the whole... you have to understand... Yeah, there is no third option, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're either not
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding sensuality, which means you're meditating with it, and all your efforts revolve around it, or you're making the effort to undo your wrong views in regard to your own desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by doing so, the nature of those desires will become apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, what is the true gratification in the desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the true danger?
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is the true escape?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why that's the only meditation that Buddha praised.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that withdrawal from sensuality is synonymous for jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, jhāna is the result of your withdrawal from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, I don't think it hurts to re-emphasize, when I say withdrawal, it doesn't mean like you shut your door, pull your blinds, and currently you don't have any desire coming in your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means internally surmounting it with your mind by understanding for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: People, most people are just driven around by their desires because they don't have a clue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why or how and to what extent they are controlled by them?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the first thing you need to do is say no to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then endure that pain and then eventually you might be able to understand the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what it meant you surmounted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what it describes, that sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: You carry on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, read those, what it says, when it says the Buddha, the meditation that the Buddha did not praise.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not, not, eh... Having not abandoned the sensuality,
[SPEAKER_01]: Still being liable to sensuality, not knowing the escape from that sensuality, he meditates.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he calls himself a meditator and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, unless you have surmounted, abandoned, understood the escape from sensuality, by the way, not from particular sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, the nature of sense desire that you are liable to, you're not liable to anymore, that's your right meditation and that's the necessary condition for jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not even jhāna, yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a pre-course.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no jhāna without it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And practicing that will have to result in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot result in anything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why when the Buddha said in other suttas, in more concise ways, when he would describe what is the right meditation, he would just describe practice of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it already implies a thorough withdrawal from sense domain, thorough abandonment of sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which probably undoes, like, 85% of all the wrong views that people carry are based on their sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, sensuality is called, like, weakener, the hindrances in sensuality, weakening of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, without sensuality, people will much quicker understand the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get the right view, be fully liberated.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the sensuality that keeps you bound with your own ignorance, through your own choices of binding yourself, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that sensuality, in essence, is the valuing of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: We said that in other talks.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, oh, I have this raging desire or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's way, way more general than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: More, more primordial than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's literally an attitude of you gratuitously maintaining value in experience of pleasure of any kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you value pleasure for no reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no reason to value pleasure more than pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, why is pleasure valuable?
[SPEAKER_01]: Simply because it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the pleasure of... the pleasure, basically, confuses you into valuing the pleasure as this thing that's worthy to develop, to protect, to gain, to increase.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you don't value the pleasure,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you would not basically be subject to that perpetual desire that is then seeking that pleasure as the goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know, again, it can be pleasure of a sexual intercourse, or food, or simply some lovely peaceful music, or a beautiful sunset vista and a cool breeze.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're seeking that out for the sake of pleasure on account of your body, on account of your senses, it's sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't seek it out on account of that pleasure of your body, then it's just agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the pleasure of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why, yes, you can sit on top of a mountain and admire the view, for sensual reasons, or not for sensual reasons, if you basically have abandoned that gratuitous value of pleasure being valuable in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, certain things, certain acts must stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot possibly do them without the value of sensuality, such as sexual integrals.
[SPEAKER_01]: As we said, that's impossible to do without already being within the perception of that sensual value.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, engaging in such acts means you're already implying the value of that, gratuitous value of that pleasure in general.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, if you go around living your life, existing, and on the level of that existence, pleasure is the value for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will then be going left and right, seeking things that will provide you with pleasure, because you value it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Naturally, if pleasure is on your mind, so whatever you do is for the sake of experiencing pleasure, because that's your goal, by having that value.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that value that you carry is before you engage with sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you're liable to the desire towards sense objects, because you actually carry on that lack of perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: You value pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Valuing the pleasure is the result of the lack of perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you, however, develop perspective on the value of pleasure,
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize that it's completely not valuable at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean, oh, now I need to experience pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the other extreme.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just means, I must remove the value of feeling of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because what is valuable?
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing valuable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just assume that it is, and you live your whole life according to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, feeling is not... it's... it comes and goes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I taste agreeable food, I recognize it as agreeable, but because I don't have the value of pleasure...
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not have desire for more of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's the more general context of valuing the pleasure that then determines how much pleasure you get, and as in, then creates the discrepancy for wanting more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the value of pleasure, it's on one level, and sense objects and pleasures you get from it, it's on another.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the desire is insatiable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're looking, basically, for it, where it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your desire is that value of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the Buddha said, that delight in pleasure, as in, I delight in the prospect of experiencing agreeable sense objects and feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: In general, I delight in that prospect.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the gratification of my pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else is secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you eating the cake, or admiring the vista, or chasing down relationships, or whatever, for the sake of sensual gratification, all that is secondary to you already gratifying your pleasure by allowing that value to control you, by maintaining the value of pleasure in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, what happens, or what could happen if you stop maintaining the value of pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Does that mean you would go in pain?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, if you ask yourself now, do I value pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I'm not engaging with anything sensual.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can drop that value.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can say, I don't... you can actually drop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can drop it, and then you forget about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you keep reminding yourself, and the more you dwell on it, the clearer it becomes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the whole point of understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: The nature of understanding is, you make the effort to clarify things that need to be understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once that perspective becomes thoroughly understood, you can't drop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't forget about it, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what I'm trying to say is that now, when people would think, oh, if I abandon value of pleasure, it's implicitly assumed, oh, that means everything will be painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is just ask yourself now, when you are not surrounded by sense objects, you are neither in pain nor in pleasure now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, things are a bit rough in this jungle, but we are used to it, so it doesn't bother us.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there are no other things of
[SPEAKER_01]: Agreeable or pleasant nature inciting either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you ask yourself, okay, so in this sort of neutral environment, am I liable to sensuality?
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, if things change, if things become more comfortable, more agreeable, will the sense desire arise in me?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you say, if you recognize that it will, means, okay, so I still value experiencing pleasure at some point, sometime.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you realize that value that exists right here, right now, is actually existing on account of this neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not engaging in pleasure now, that reminds you of pleasure, that there you want more pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're quite withdrawn from pleasure now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, somehow, the mind could still value centrality on account of which you have the future sense desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is no value,
[SPEAKER_01]: Of that pleasure in general, future sense desire cannot manifest in you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why don't you abandon that value right here, right now, on account of this neutral feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Consequently, by actually gratuitously maintaining that value of pleasure, this neutral feeling is actually experienced painfully.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you value pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your threshold.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your gratuitous criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the Buddha said, when you don't recognize the neutral feeling that's here, it's going to be felt as unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you recognize it, it's going to be felt as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that pleasure of neutral feeling is a good type of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a pleasure you cannot crave for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, see, it's not rooted, it's not determined by this value of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I see.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it sounds to me like you drop the value, here and now, of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't want that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need that anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't value it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It hasn't given me any lasting anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It hasn't given me enough anything that I can resort to depend on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you mean, you allow that idea to endure, to possess, to protect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cultivate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think about it further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, see, now you drop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You understand it hasn't provided...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you have all that essential thoughts come in your mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but I can remind myself, it's not valuable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I realize that, if I really realize that, the burden of the value of getting...
[SPEAKER_00]: I must... Oh, yeah, you feel the burden drop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: You feel the release.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that release is that neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're released into peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which you would have... you always had in front of you, but you were not recognizing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, when you have a thought, say, okay, you do have, on some physical level, you're restrained, and you recognize, I'll never engage with this anymore, it never provides any satisfaction, it's just burden, further disturbance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're established within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, on a more subtler level, your mind might have a thought or something about sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I must not think that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: When that thought arises, include that thought in this context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't forget the context on account of the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now I have these thoughts, but this value remains un... this, sorry, the new value of devalued sensuality remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, allow thoughts to endure, sensual thoughts, if they manifested, allow them to endure against the backdrop of devalued sensuality, because that's how you devalue the thoughts as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you forget about the perspective, and go ahead and deal with the thoughts, and get rid of the thoughts, and oppress the thoughts, and not think about the thoughts, and duh-duh-duh-duh-duh-duh-duh-duh... Ah, well, they hook you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might not go physically and engage with sensuality, but you are revolving around it by fighting the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you just want to not lose that right perspective, yoniso, manasikāra, even when the... whether it's the physical prospect, verbal prospect, mental prospect, the deep values of sensuality as the new value
[SPEAKER_01]: And the longer you maintain it and protect it, the more of anything like... like the discrepancy caused by sensual desire will burn away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Scorch.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the Buddha... what was the simile?
[SPEAKER_01]: The... the heat up... heated up pan.
[SPEAKER_01]: You throw and instantly the water will evaporate, if it's really, really hot.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your pan.
[SPEAKER_01]: The hot pan is that new value of devalued sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't matter what sensual object come in your sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Evaporates instantly, because that's... you don't stop it to deal with it, you just maintain the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's valueless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or another simile of eating the food and not catching the bait, like the deer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you not take the food that has the bait?
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't forget about the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see the bait, but you know the bait, and you get to recognize where the bait is, and you don't eat that food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you go around and eat everything else you want, except the one that would hook you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can then have plenty of actions aimed at, oh, I'll lay down because my back hurts, as the Buddha would say, or, oh, this is agreeable grove, let us spend some time here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, for Pratyūjana, non-free from sensuality, you would think, oh, but the Buddha has desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, not the desires that you think of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you start the practice, you're fully within centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have a neutral point from which you can see arahant type of desire and putujana type of desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are the putujana type of desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you can do is work your way out from the inside of that desire and then what you have is not a desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yes, your intention can still value avoiding discomfort, for example, and it will not be central.
[SPEAKER_01]: But unless you're free, if you're not free from sensuality in that fundamental manner, as the Buddha said, you don't know the liability, the gratification liability, danger and escape from it, then even the innocent intentions towards agreeable, your dwelling, your sleeping place, your food will be thoroughly sensual, because you made it so.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the danger is that value.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The danger is not like, oh, see, the danger is if I go out and seek things out, and then things can go not the way I want them to.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all the result.
[SPEAKER_01]: The danger is implicit before you engage with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, gratification is implicit before you engage with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, the escape is implicit before you engage with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But gratification is the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, danger is within the gratification, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gratification is the aspect of the same thing that's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognizing the gratification as the same aspect of the danger is how you get the escape from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the... just that value, just that happiness, that delight, as the Buddha would say, on account of valuing the pleasure, that's the gratification of the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the extent of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, what is the danger?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that utterly, like virtually, almost abstract value, and it's abstract because you never stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you're never restrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: You never step back from the sense objects to get perspective on them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, second, you never think about, wait, why do I value pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, why do I move from discomfort into comfort?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, let me try.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sometimes the Buddha would say, well,
[SPEAKER_01]: They would ask him, or should you do these ascetic practices?
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, well, let those who know that those practices would bring the wholesome to increase, unwholesome to decrease, let them do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sometimes that means, let me go in the adverse enduring of the elements and hardship, because I recognize that as devaluing, automatic devaluing of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not a guarantee.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to know where the value is, and what, like, oh, this value is gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must basically challenge that value internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that does not necessarily mean that everybody can do the same practice externally in terms of ascetic practices and endurance and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: To some extent, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But to what extent, how far you need to take that, that depends on... well, depends on the individual.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, when you recognize that, like, literally, the danger of that value is that you have this value of pleasure
[SPEAKER_01]: From the level of like, oh, pleasure of satisfying your curiosity, to the level of pleasure of, you know, the wildest unrestrained music, drugs, alcohol, sexual intercourse, the whole thing, it's all within the same domain of, I value pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you realize, because you choose to value pleasure, you make yourself liable, you seek it out over there, in this wild world, which you're not in control of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like people, I mean, people work, like, you know, their hands to the bone, just so they can earn, just so they can provide themselves with pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: The family, children, spouses, the whole thing, it's all under the value of, I just want pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can be moderate about it, I can be restrained to some extent, or I cannot be so, but fundamentally, either way, I still value pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that, I am liable, literally, to the danger of this very dangerous world.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have confidence in pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, see, you would not suffer if things fall and break and snap your arm in half.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it would be uncomfortable, but you will not have mental despair and fear on account of that happening to you, if you don't have any desire towards using that arm for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have already... see, the implicit value of pleasure on that mental level creates the value of the body as your tool toward the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if something happens to the body that prevents you from gaining the pleasure later on, that's then the real pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's all what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is dukkha?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not getting what you want is dukkha, and getting what you don't want is dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, having desire towards this, not having that, is dukkha, and having desire against this, and having that, is dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't get rid of things when you want, is dukkha, and you can't get things when you want, is dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, experience as a whole is dukkha, because of that central value.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're liable to this mass of suffering indirectly, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, your value of sensuality is mental, existential, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your value of pleasure, on account of it, you go along with the society, with what people do, with the values, and family, and work, and earning.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that, all of that is within the big domain, the big bubble of valuing pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Comfort, security, all of it, all of it, all of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is very, very uncertain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know it's uncertain, but you lose the perspective on that uncertainty, because you value pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Valuing pleasure for gratuitous reason makes you fundamentally irrational.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's kind of, yeah, removing just that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, so you don't need to destroy the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to remove your value of the pleasure in regard to the world, and then
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing can affect you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You lose your life, you lose your health, because there was no endgame to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But with the value of pleasure, there is always an endgame of more pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there is nothing for you to suffer on account of, because you don't value pleasure, which means you don't automatically devalue pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't automatically fear the prospect of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're indifferent towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, like, in modern world, comfort is one of the kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, most people don't even see how much they depend on... gregarious extent... amounts of comfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like soft beds, and duvets, and pillows, and carpets, and socks, and just... just comfort, comfort, comfort, comfort, comfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you wouldn't even necessarily think of that as centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, it's fully, completely within the value... Why do you value comfort?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, because you value pleasure over it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do you become irrationally terrified, anxious, at the prospect of sensory strain, at the prospect of physical discomfort for a period of time?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, like when people... you see them, like, when they go hiking or something, and after, like, half an hour of just fatigue sets in, how cranky they become.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're getting something which you do not value at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not enough pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pain, discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It pushes you against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You create this gaping hole that can never be fulfilled by valuing that pleasure on the mental level, but the only way you can seek it out is on the level of your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you don't value pleasure when it's there...
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no discrepancy that you need to fulfill.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't value pleasure,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not there, means whatever's there is fine in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the seen, there will just be the seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the heard, there will just be the heard, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can literally then continue with the same principle and say, in the felt, there will be just the felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the perceived, there will be just the perceived.
[SPEAKER_01]: There will be no more misconceiving towards the future, the future kind of implications and desires that are rooted in you, gratuitously holding on to the value of pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why in that sutta, the Buddha gave the simile of those Licchavis, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: They were sleeping on the hard beds with wooden blocks as pillows.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for as long as they do that, no other kingdom can conquer them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the future, in the future, the time will come, when they will go soft.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will, they will, they will have soft footwear.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will sleep on soft beddings, have soft pillows.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will become fair with soft feet and hands, skin.
[SPEAKER_00]: Get up after the sun comes up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, lazy in getting up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then,
[SPEAKER_01]: They'll be overwhelmed by the kingdom, no problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he gave the same comparison to the monk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Monk who does... who sleeps with a wooden pillow on a hard surface, Māra will have much harder time finding access in him.
[SPEAKER_01]: A monk who wears very comfortable robes, lives in a comfortable environment, with abundance of food, abundance of comfort, abundance of mattresses, abundance of pillows, abundance of heat, abundance of dry weather, abundance of very, very nice things, they're not sensual, for layman's terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just comfortable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, sleeping on a pillow is not like a raging sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, because of that, you are liable to a raging sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the comfort is just the subtle way, as I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the the pleasure of curiosity, unless you abandon the value of sensual... of that... of pleasant, on the level of mind, even that sensual.
[SPEAKER_00]: How much more...
[SPEAKER_00]: In the domain of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's fully within the domain of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a prey to... a liable prey to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're in its feeding ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, if the monk does expose himself to discomfort, not, you know, you don't need to be stabbing yourself and cutting yourself and torturing yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just don't make all the excess effort towards the comfort and then you'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, valuing pleasure, again, is the entry point into the being hunted by sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, yes, but not entry point as if you were outside and then somehow you make a choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are already within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, valuing the pleasure is a framework.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically your existence is already within the value of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the karmabhāva, the being of sensuality, is abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's so difficult to give up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a part...
[SPEAKER_01]: Your intentions are already the result of that, of that value, of that lack of perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your choices...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to kind of undo it from the inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: While you're affected by it, you need to find a way out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is possible, if you start looking in the right things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that you should look at.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or what we've been saying for last hour or so.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the point is, you recognize you value pleasure, and that is the framework for any experience of pleasant or unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, through that framework, pleasure will be created for more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through that framework, pain will be created for less.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through that framework, neutral feeling will be basically ignored.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you abandon that framework, neutral feeling will not be ignored and will be pleasant and you will not be trying to get rid of the pain and you will not seek the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, pleasure will arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: In pleasant, there will just be the pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: In unpleasant, there will just be unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: In neutral, there will just be neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no seeking, trying to get away.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: The discrepancy of seeking... See, seeking is already a discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you have and what you seek.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's created by that perpetual maintenance, feeding off the current, present, here and now, value of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what would have meant,
[SPEAKER_01]: Other things in me, right here, right now, on account of which future sense desire can manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, is this framework still maintained by me?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I still valuing the pleasure, however implicitly?
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you see it, by seeing it, you can actually abandon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, let me devalue it, because it's not valuable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me regard it just for the amusement's sake, the value of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me regard it as dangerous, perilous, painful, resulting in charnel grounds being filled.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, guess what?
[SPEAKER_01]: It is that, and because you've been valuing it how it actually is, you get to see it for what it actually is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, initially, you took it on faith, that the value of pleasant is very, very dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you start applying it, you get to see it because it actually, factually is so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it weren't so, the Buddha wouldn't have said, oh, you should abandon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: For your own welfare.